"Fecal Transplants for Aging
and Weight Loss"
Hippocrates said,
All diseases begin in the gut.
Previously, I've talked
about fecal transplants,
transferring the stool of healthy
people into the colons of patients
suffering from inflammatory bowel
disease, multiple sclerosis,
even psychiatric problems
like depression, bipolar disorder,
and alcoholism to repopulate
their gut with good bacteria
in hopes of improving
their conditions.
What about fecal
transplants for aging?
Might the fountain of youth
be a fountain of poop?
If you give mice
with accelerated aging
a fecal transplant from healthy
mice, they perk up and live longer,
but what about
human poop?
We don’t yet have human-
to-human aging data,
but we do have mice
transplanted
with fecal matter
from a centenarian.
Mice fed poop from a 101-year-old
versus poop from a 70-year-old.
Lipofuscin is an age pigment
that’s widely used
as a biomarker for aging,
and lipofuscin accumulated
significantly less
in the brain tissue of centenarian
poop-fed mice raising the possibility
that we will one day be using
centenarian fecal matter
for anti-aging purposes
and to promote healthy aging.
Why bathe in the
blood of virgins
when you can dine on
the dung of the venerable?
To be continued,
once human-to-human
data are published.
Poop you may want to avoid
is from overweight stool donors,
given this case report about weight
gain after a fecal transplant.
A 32-year-old woman
“had always been of normal weight”
until...she received a fecal
transplant from a healthy
but overweight
donor – her daughter.
After the transplant
she became obese,
gaining more
than 40 pounds.
“She said she felt like there
was a switch inside her body,”
her gastroenterologist reported.
“No matter how much
she ate or exercised,
she couldn’t take
the weight off.
She’s very frustrated.”
The same thing
happens in mice.
Giving mice fecal pellets
from an obese mouse
resulted in nearly a doubling
in fat mass
compared to lean mouse pellets
despite eating
significantly fewer calories.
This proves gut flora can play
a pivotal role in obesity…in mice.
What about in people?
Researchers decided
to study pairs
of human twins
“discordant” for obesity,
meaning one twin was fat,
the other skinny.
What would happen if you
switched their microbiomes?
The siblings may
have been squeamish;
so, the researchers
reverted to mice again.
Mice fed stool from the obese
twin rapidly swelled in size
but not those fed
from the lean twin,
despite comparable
calorie intakes.
Cohousing the mice together
prevented the weight gain;
however, the lean-type
bacteria jumped over to rescue
the mouse fed stool
from the obese twin, but—
and here’s the critical point—
only in the context
of a healthier diet.
The microbial cure only
worked when the mice were fed
low saturated fat, high-fiber
diets, which makes sense
since the lean-type bacteria
appeared to be fiber feeders.
“Together,” the researchers
concluded,
“these results…illustrate how
a diet high in saturated fats
and low in fruits and vegetables
can select against
human gut bacteria…
associated with leanness.”
The results of the twin study
suggest that the role
of our gut flora
in obesity is just to help take
fuller advantage
of a more healthful diet.
So, if the twins had actually
swapped their stool,
the obese twin might have only
lost weight if they combined
the microbial makeover
with healthier eating
to aid the colonization
of the better bugs.
With the new bacteria
on board, though,
the healthier diet could have
resulted in more weight loss,
even eating the same
number of calories.
But you don’t really know...
until you put it to the test.
There had been previous
published attempts,
randomized double-blind
placebo-controlled trials
showing no weight
loss benefit
to getting lean donor
fecal transplants,
but they kept people
on the same crappy diets
that led to obesity
in the first place.
Who cares if you keep
putting slimming,
fiber-feeding bacteria
into your gut,
if you don’t give them
any fiber to eat?
They’ll just starve
and die right off.
So, maybe you have to do both,
pairing gut bacteria modulation
with a dietary intervention.
But, if you do a plant-based
diet along with a transplant
and they lose
a bunch of weight,
how do you know if the transplant
had anything to do with it?
Which brings us to this study,
What they did is put people
on a healthy plant-based diet
supplemented with green tea
and green smoothies
until...they lost
about 20 pounds
over 6 months and grabbed
a fecal sample.
Then, they were randomized
to spend the rest of the year
constantly seeding their gut
with the healthy microbiome
they had achieved at maximal
weight loss or to placebo capsules.
The question was once they go
back to their regular diets,
would those getting the constant
infusion of their own skinny poop
help them keep the weight off? Yes.
They found that participants
who lost weight on a healthy diet
and were then fed capsules
containing fecal matter collected
during the diet period for months
after the maximal weight loss,
regained less weight than
participants given placebo capsules.
So, the plant-based diet
appeared to produce
the optimal fecal microbiome
for preventing weight regain.
But rather than eating
your own plant-based poo,
why not just stick
with the plant-based diet.